as always you can click on the timestamp
in the description as well as here to
skip this longish introduction the
theories of everything channel is back
with a new season starting with last
week's AMA which will be in the
description from this point forward
there will be new content approximately
once a week sometimes even more
frequently today's guests are Carl
friston michae 11an and Chris field the
former two have been on this channel and
mentioned several times prior whereas
Chris Fields is making his debut Chris
Fields is a research in topological
Quantum field Theory as well as
information Theory and publishes work on
what constitutes an observer Carl
friston is a professor of neuroscience
at the University College London and is
the inventor of the free energy
principle Michael Levan is the
Developmental and synthetic biologist at
the tus University the links to all
their previous podcasts on the tow
channel will be in the description my
name is Kurt jongle I'm a torontonian
filmmaker with a background in
mathematical physics dedicated to the
explication quote quote of the
variegated terrain of theories of
everything primarily from a theoretical
physics perspective but as well as
trying to understand what role does
Consciousness have as constitutive
reality is it emergent is it fundamental
now the goals of theol lotions is to
interject seldomly if at all allowing
each guest to give their perspectives on
one another's thoughts essentially
giving us the experience of a fly on the
wall for the sorts of academic
conversations that would ordinarily
occur behind closed doors spur ing
research in real time one of the central
issues of today's podcast is the concept
of babbling which I haven't heard
discussed virtually anywhere else
outside of Child Development or language
acquisition though it can be generalized
metaphorically perhaps even literally to
the vacuum fluctuations to interpret
what vacuum fluctuations they're doing
as an indicator of the universe's
protoconsciousness that is the universe
babbling to understand itself but I
won't spoil the surprise if you'd like
to hear more podcasts like these then do
consider going to
patreon.com jongle as the patrons and
the sponsors are the only reasons that
I'm able to do this full-time with
regard to sponsors there's one for
today's episode and that is brilliant
during the winter break I decided to
brush up on the fundamentals of
information Theory which is what
Constructor theory is heavily based in
and I'd like to do an episode on that so
I took brilliant's course on knowledge
and uncertainty and random variables and
after taking that course I could finally
see why entropy is defined the way it is
why the formula for it is is extremely
natural there are plenty of courses you
can even learn group Theory which is
what's being referenced when you hear
that the internal symmetries of the
standard model is U1 cross su2 cross su3
those are Le groups visit brilliant.org
to to get 20% off the annual
subscription I recommend that you don't
stop before four lessons just keep
pursuing until you've accomplished at
least four and I think you'll be greatly
surprised at the ease at which you can
now comprehend subjects you pre
previously had a difficult time grocking
and now on to today's episode which is
one that I'm extremely lucky to be able
to present to you all you'll be able to
see the mutual respect that the guests
have for one another we start off
actually by asking what is it that you
respect about each other's work enjoy
this the olution between Carl friston
Michael Lan and Chris Fields I've been
extremely excited about this so
Professor what do you find unique about
Carl's and Chris's work and what is it
that you respect about
them well what a great question I think
all all discussions should uh should
should start with that question um uh
there's a lot I mean I think I think the
most basic thing I can say is this that
I'm I'm often asked by by conference
organizers and students as far as who
who they should follow yeah who's
whose's work they should um keep track
of and and so I keep lists and uh and
and Carl and Chris are at the very top
of two specific lists for me and I'm
just always amazed about this is that
the first the first is that um both of
them are experts in at least three
different fields probably more so so so
they have the ability to kind of merge
really deep um understanding of
different fields I mean there's many
people that are experts in in one thing
but I'm just uh I'm just always
incredibly impressed as how they uh both
of them can weave together a really deep
Knowledge from from a from diverse
disciplines and and and and that leads
to the kind of the second thing that
that I'm really inspired by which is
just the kind of the sheer density of
new ideas you know it's hard enough to
push things in one just kind of one know
Direction and do science and so on but
both both Chris and Carl's work um
consistently make me think in new ways
uh give me ideas I never never thought
of before it's just just just amazing so
yeah so I'm super excited to be able to
work with both of them and to to have
this discussion great Chris same
question but toward Michael and
Carl uh well I can say that uh one thing
I certainly
admire is that
uh Michael and Carl are both top level
biologists who are interested in
theory and and deeply involved in theory
and have a deep understanding of uh
Theory and um something that I
enormously admire is that both of them
have that interest and yet are deeply
engaged in practical
applications uh Carl in mental health
and Mike in regenerative
biology and
that's a rare
combination Carl what is it that you
find unique about Michael's and Chris's
work and what do you particularly
respect about them as people
perhaps I deliberately haven't rehearsed
an answer so what I say comes from the
heart um so with Mike um I first met him
vicariously through a friend giovan pulo
um and didn't really know very much
about his work until I visited his
website then I realized how influential
and important he was and then I
recognized all the little bulletins you
get on um social media and emails I
started to recognize his name and
realized that he he was quite a mover
and Shaker out there what I like about
both of them they both think really
really fuss and they both think out of
the box um um so I think what
characterizes both of their thinking
really is just to ask what is a thing in
and of itself without making any prior
assumptions and then putting it back
together um from basic principles and
coming up with some sometimes
counterintuitive um conclusions um but
for me almost uh universally exactly the
same counterintuitive conclusions I've
come to after about 10 years of thinking
about a particular problem but never
dare tell anybody but they do they write
it down very
eloquently they're very very productive
um Chris I've known for less Long and
I've met him via Mike um and um in
addition to that in the same way that
many people I meet have physics Envy um
I've got Quantum Envy about Chris you he
just seems to know so much think about
the world in a way which I don't have
that sort of fluency in but it sounds
really really useful and and quite
correct so I'm hoping if I hang around
long enough some of it will rub off on
me or at least be able to use the words
without sounding like an
idiot what would be an example of this
out of thebox thinking you mentioned
thinking about what is a thing in and of
itself what
else there are numerous examples um the
first thing just came to mind was just
putting together fundamental questions
about self-organization if you were
verel you're sort of autois self-
assembly self- construction if you're a
chemist it would be self assembly if
you're a theoretical biologist um you
will be wondering about why on Earth is
it that um multicellular organisms form
because there's a deep Paradox there you
know if it is the case that I have to
have a surface as a little organ then
some of my have cells have to stop
replicating and yet that is in direct
contradiction to the principles of
natural selection I'm going to turn off
my reproductive capacity my adaptive
Fitness so defined in a in a theoretical
context so just really s grasping the
nettle and thinking about well these
things exist what principles could
possibly explain the paradoxes when
looked at from sort of the unilateral
the monothematic view of natural
selection for example or The
monothematic View of self-organization
in physics so thinking out of the box
literally in this instance um entails
being able to take multiple perspectives
on a particular problem and seeing the
contradictions and seeing how they can
be resolved now that would be one of
many
examples there was a paper and I'm
afraid I can't remember the specific one
perhaps Mike and Chris will be able to
enlighten me but there was one paper
written I I think about a year or two
ago where they actually listed I think
there were 50
basic conclusions about the the
fundaments and and the um the nature of
self-organization and self as distinct
from other uh in any system and you just
listing 15 really interesting points and
predictions all of which either um I'm
sure will be formally demonstr
analytically um true uh or at least
yield or be amable to uh a mathematical
analysis
um or would be empirically verifiable um
you know over the next few
years what was that baby there was a
paper in Neuroscience of
Consciousness uh arguing for a an
approach to Consciousness that Spann
philogyny and we were very interested in
that
paper specifically to look at uh
bacteria and single cells
and
um facultative multicellular such as
microbial
biofilms and
ask what do these systems know about the
world how do they see the
world uh how does it how does eoli
perceive the world for
example and we suggested that the the
answer is in in terms of of the sorts of
things that we call Taste and
viscosity but that experiences of taste
and viscosity are perfectly good kinds
of experiences and that if we think
about how these kinds of
systems deal with their
worlds and solve problems within their
worlds that that would give us a more
unified understanding of what it meant
to be U A system that was
aware and so you're trying to use eoli
as a means of understanding yourself or
humans by the way is this a project do
you feel like your undertaking is an
attempt for you to understand yourself
or you trying to understand humans like
I'm I'm wondering is this more
philanthropic or it's selfish and then
it bleeds into the
philanthropic well I I actually also
want to understand
eoli I be we have we don't have a great
understanding of of the lives of other
organisms Professor Levan what puzzle do
you find most important what do you
think about on an semi daily basis or
even perhaps multiple times a day and
then we'll go around the table here with
Chris fields and Carl friston next and
then it's essentially me taking a back
seat and allowing you all to free
just for the audience to know I know you
all know this template already yeah um
so so the thing I think about many times
today uh has to do with the scaling of
cognition so I want to understand two
two two major things one is how it is
that uh some collection of competent
Parts comes together to form a an
emergent self with preferences goals
memories um cognitive capacities that
belong to it but not to the individual
parts so I want to understand how that
how that emerges how the goals of you
know sort of humble um simple simple
kinds of systems scale up into much more
grandiose goals that we see and during
during development during Behavior Uh
you know during culture and so on and
and I'm and I'm also very interested in
uh the sort of the left side of that
Spectrum where does it begin you know is
there really a zero on the Spectrum I
think that uh all of us here would agree
that there is a spectrum for these
things it's not a set of binary
categories but what happens at the very
left side of the spectrum and so one of
the first questions you know when we get
to that that um that I had written down
to ask both both Chris and caros to sort
of comment on what does the what does
the ven diagram look like of of the set
of things that are alive versus the set
of things that are cognitive yeah how do
those two categories relate to each
other do they overlap as one a subset of
the other and what really happens at the
very beginning you know like can we can
we develop a kind of um which which I
think I think both of them have been
working on a kind of basically a kind of
pan psychism that doesn't doesn't sort
of paint on new um cognitive mysteries
on top of a physics that works perfectly
well but instead to try and to try to
view physics from the bottom up as
having already a useful cognitive lens
on it and and how does that help us to
build up cognition so that's that's
something that I think about every
day
Chris
um I I thought every day or almost every
day for a long time about
why we humans um see objects embedded in
SpaceTime so why do we see
things that we treat as independent of
each other and why do we see them
operate on them interact with them uh
think about them as embedded in this
coordinate system that we call
space and uh equally important why do we
see them as
maintaining their identities as
things over this other coordinate that
we call
time
Carl um well I have to confess I spend
recurrently most of my time thinking
about me um but in an acad MC sense you
how do I work so it's a curious mixture
of introspection and trying to
understand why I can introspect in from
the perspective or through the lens of a
physicist so I I spend most of my time
dissembling preconceptions the gifts
that uh our sence has given us um and
try to um reassemble them in relation to
physics density Dynamics uh you know the
the has to be articulated in terms of
the kind of math that a physicist would
use which would be you effectively
differential equations and the calculus
of variations and having done that there
are so many um there are sufficient
number of moving Parts but not that many
but the combinatorics then lead you to
the the kinds of questions that Mike was
was talking about so you know what
different ways could this um physics of
sentience um be manifest what possible
ways could it be manifest and how does
that address the distinction between um
things particles creatures um that would
show the kind of sense making and to my
mind an important aspect is planning
that dis would disambiguate them from
other natural kinds or particular kinds
that don't have that kind of facility
and what underwrites that um so that's
what I spend most of my time doing I
have to say in conversation both with um
Mike and Chris and other people um that
you can easily get distracted um in in
in a rightful way um by um thinking
about that mechanics in exactly what
Chris was talking to which is a sort of
scale-free way but in my rhetoric that
scale freeness speaks more to the
coupling between different scales that
Mike was alluding to um so how does this
um mechanics this physics of sentience
which which I understand largely in
terms of probability Theory and um
effectively basing um probability Theory
um so what you have is a basing
mechanics how does that basy mechanics
apply at one scale and another scale and
then of course the big questions is how
do the two scales Caple to each other so
that that that for me is something that
I I find myself increasingly pressed
upon uh largely through conversations
and collaborations um but you that does
mean that I spend a lot of my time
thinking about that and you're writing
demos of mathematical equations trying
to trying to get to the um the uh the
underpinnings of
it Mike I see you nodding so what is it
about what Carl said I'm sorry Professor
11 I apologize and what is it that what
is it that professor friston said that
has you feeling like you agree with it
well as as as usual I mean he said it
perfectly I couldn't I couldn't say it
better myself I think that's uh that's
that's exactly the kind of um uh
research agenda that I'm interested in I
mean that's that really is the kind of a
a very good um description of of what I
think we're all looking for in a certain
sense is there a difference between
cognition and Consciousness is one
distinct is there overlap is one a
subset I I actually can't conceive of
cognition without Consciousness which I
I prefer to call awareness
um not just to be perverse but because
in many
cases Consciousness is used in a way
that implicitly means
self-consciousness whereas awareness is
often Ed in a way that does not make
that
implication
uh and it's I I find it difficult to
conceive of cognition without any kind
of awareness at all
so so so could I just so I'll ask a
question then based on what what Chris
just said and and and what when you know
and what Carl has to say about it so so
what do you think about the so-called
hard problem is there in fact a hard
problem at
all I would um I would take Andy Clark's
view on this uh who has worked closely
with with David Charmers
um I I I don't think so no I I I don't
think that the hard problem in and of
itself is um is the um interesting um
focus of inquiry I think the um the move
that I see in philosophy um has been to
the meta problem or The Meta hard
problem which is um as Andy clar puts it
quite succinctly is why do we spend so
much time puzzling about why we are
aware um so just asking that question um
speaks to I think the nature of the hard
problem which is a sort of very much a
second order meta um a meta capability
that we can um make sense of our own
sense making and we um associate that
with selfhood so one has to ask the
question what kinds of systems again I
say particles or creatures would have
the capacity to represent selfhood and
furthermore represent the
counterfactuals that would enable you to
ask the question why I'm my conscious
that immediately just logically
presupposes that there is an alternative
hypothesis or other counterfactual that
I'm not conscious so imagine now you're
talking to um a creature you're talking
to me that has this capacity to imagine
counterfactuals that cannot exist so
that's a remarkable capacity to have you
know um from my point of view a sort of
internal World model or a generative
model where counterfactuals can exist is
is quite remarkable I I don't imagine
that a a thermostat or a virus or an
eoli will have a sufficiently
sophisticated set of you know um
electrochemical uh Dynamics or kinetics
that would enable them to physically
represent counterfactuals of this sort
and I could go on um you know the usual
line of argument is why do we have
models why do we have the capacity to
represent counterfactuals and the um us
end up with saying yes you have to have
them just if you
um contemplate things that plan so if
things plan they have to have um an
ability to simulate the
future because they have to simulate or
represent at some Elemental level the
consequences of their action upon the
world and if they have now the capacity
to represent something that has not yet
happened they in the future then they
now have the capacity to represent
counterfactual outcomes so I think the
the metah hard problem inherits simply
because we have a sufficiently temporary
deep generative model that can represent
the consequences of our actions and of
course using the word our implies some
kind of Elemental agency and some kind
of selfhood because it's only me that's
doing the acting and the consequences of
my action not your action uh so so in in
that sense I think that the hard problem
um sort of pales into into in
significance in relation to the The Meta
problem of why it is that we have
philosophers can I can I pursue that
just a little bit I think you rais an
extraordinarily interesting point here
Carl and so i' want to ask you uh from a
philogenetic perspective
um do you think
that
organisms that can
plan
necessarily are able to represent
multiple
counterfactuals so let's give an example
uh suppose you're a cheetah chasing a
gazelle
of your planning your moves while
looking at the gazelle's
moves and your objective is
Success you think that the cheetah
worries about the other counterfactual
condition where the gazelle isn't caught
or does it just represent this one
counterfactual condition that is in a
sense the G
State that's excellent question I
personally think that
um and when I answer these questions I
think
how would I simulate this how would I
put a cheer in silico and integrate um
according to the differential equations
that must be present under certain
assumptions um and my guess is that the
cheetah chasing the gazelle would as you
say just be pursuing a path of least
action and would not have an explicit
representation of alternative paths so
it would be responding in the moment in
a reflexive habitual way so that's a
really important question because
if we don't have or all of our behavior
is just a manifestation of pursuing
those passive least resistance or
mathematically those you know Paths of
of space action um then there is no
counterfactual to select from and there
is no notion of planning in the sense of
I am going to do this as opposed to that
but that doesn't mean to say biological
organisms um don't have the capacity to
um plan multiple Futures and I'll just
give give you one real simple example of
um um the your our brains and I would
imagine even the brains of reptiles to a
certain extent um H being able to plan
multiple um actions in the future and
that's in eye movements so if I just
take one of the simplest problems in
terms of planning or perhaps not the
simplest but one of the um the the the
the problems of planning that have to be
resolved within um you know several 100
milliseconds given that we have to
choose where to look every 250
milliseconds in order to gather the
right kind of information to make to
Constructor the scene in which we are
situated and coming back to your
preoccupation Chris your you how on
Earth do we then explain these
sparse um cadic
samples within some frame of reference
some SpaceTime sort of how do we you
know sense make with reference to some
constructs such as space and time but uh
the point I'm making here is that the
anatomy of um many uh brains many
phenotypes does have the capacity to
represent the consequences of looking
everywhere at the same time at once
before they have looked so these are
sort of sometimes refer to as sence maps
and we know that um there are good
candidates for these sence maps for
example the Deep layers of the superior
calcul and could argue possibly some
anatomy of the pulina so if you look at
the um if you like the neuronal encoding
of the salience of where um the salience
of the next place to look what's going
to grab my attention in and make that be
manifest overtly with an eye movement to
go and look over there then there you
can interpret I think the anatomy the
ocular motor system and especially the
um that which underlies Sanic the
control ptic eye movements as
entertaining a whole range possibly
millions of potential um um uh plans of
action and the consequences and then the
brain literally selects the one that's
most likely uh which you can simulate by
doing bumper tractors on these sort of
salience maps or representations of the
the salience or the epistemic affordance
or the expected Information Gain if I
looked over here I looked over here I
looked over here I looked over here you
select that you eyes jump over there and
off you go again so I think it's a great
question in a sense speaks I think to a
certain extent to what Mike was alluding
to before that there are certain setups
or are certain sort of neuronal
electrochemical um
infrastructures out there that can be
read as just pursuing Paths of police
action in a reflexive way and there are
others that may have this um richer
structure this deeper structure that
could be
uh support the you know the the active
sentience and the sort of what I I'm
reading now as cognition if cognition
entails planning uh then I certainly
think there has to be an act of
selection in play here um selection what
does that mean from something from what
well multiple Alternatives and then we
come back to the central notion of this
this
counterfactual yeah Mike is that what
you had in mind in terms of breaking
this sort of pans psychism uh sort of
trap you different kinds of of
self-organization yeah I mean that's
certainly certainly related you know uh
the thing the thing that um and and so I
I agree with Chris's kind of gut feeling
on this I find it very difficult to
imagine cognition without some sort of
awareness or or simple Consciousness
however what what strikes me as as
different than real about the hard
problem is that unlike all the quote
unquote easy problems and maybe unlike
the meta hard problem we kind of know
the for or the shape of answers to those
questions right they're either they're
numbers or they're equations or they
lists of capacities you know we we we
know what what a proper answer would
look like and yet I I find it very hard
to imagine if we if somebody claimed to
have a a good theory of Consciousness
and I were to ask them okay well what is
the prediction of your theory in this
particular case I don't know what the
format of the answer looks like because
numbers and the typical things we get
don't do the trick they you know they're
sort of third person descriptions and so
so is the answer does the answer come in
the form of a poem is it art is it you
know something you have to literally
plug yourself into to then have that
experience like what's the I I I find it
different because I don't know what if
we had a true a correct Theory I don't
know what that theory would output you
know unlike for all these other theories
where at least we have some idea of what
the output looks
like well that's that's a meta answer to
the hard problem then that's that's very
good I heard that
before I'm sure the answer is quantum
physics that's that's what it's going to
look like if if we could if we could
understand it the answer would be in
quantum
physics Chris do you
agree well I I'd like to to back up a
little bit uh and in a sense playoff
what Carl was just saying about
Alternatives and the role of
Alternatives in the hard
problem um I mean chers drives his
arguments about the hard problem with
the alternative of
unconsciousness
and this alternative makes great
sense against the background of a
particular set of assumptions about
physics uh which
is the assumption
that nothing is going on cognitive
atively in the physical world that
there's that there's no reason to talk
about uh experience or awareness or or
anything like
that when we're talking
about um rocks or billiard balls or
planets or electrons or anything
else and in that case there is this
cut uh that is not really a cut in
scale of spatial scale or temporal scale
but is in a sense a cut in some measure
of
[Music]
complexity that suggests that below some
cut point which may be a bright line and
and maybe a fuzzy area who
knows there's the possibility
or below some cut point there there's no
awareness at all none
zero and above that cut Point there's
some possibility of
awareness and in that case one's forced
to say
how what what could be
added by complexity other than
complexity to produce
awareness and it's that intuition I
believe that drives the heart problem do
you mind explaining that a bit more what
can be added by complexity that's not
complexity that
sentence well
um yeah one way to put it is complexity
has as complexity increases some magic
has to happen and uh you suddenly get
awareness and it's not clear quite how
much complex one has to add but as soon
as one reaches the the right amount then
uh out of the blue you've got
awareness whereas without Crossing that
threshold you you had no awareness
whatsoever so there's a zero point and
the zero points somewhere on the scale
of complexity and it's nowhere near the
bottom so I think one can I can think
one can view a lot of research on
Consciousness as a way to escape that
argument so I'll consider integrated
information
Theory
uh in integrated information Theory the
Criterion for Consciousness or awareness
is actually very simple you you need to
have an internal feedback
loop and if you've got an internal
feedback back Loop you're at least a
candidate for being aware as long as
you're not embedded in something bigger
that has bigger internal feedb
backwards and
uh if one thinks about
um the work of Peter straon for
example from a philosophical
perspective his arguments toward pan
psychism
are all arguments of the form there's no
way to draw the line in the scale of
complexity and get a place where um
magic basically plausibly
happens
so I think I think chers did a real
service in in posing the problem in that
way because it forced us to think about
this idea of magic or you could call it
emergence if you wanted
to of something completely new that was
awareness now I I do agree with Carl
that quantum theory can help us dispel
the
problem uh by by being in effect a
theory that's about
awareness but we can we can get to that
further down the road do you have any
reason to believe that we're embedded in
something larger you mentioned in IIT
there's the feedback loop that is
necessary for Consciousness and you said
that one is conscious as long as one is
not embedded in something else that's of
which that is conscious like there's a
larger feedback loop there do you see
there being some larger feedback loop
some people say the universe itself is
conscious or that societies can act at
some larger level consciousness
with each of us acting as neurons in
some
sense well I would certainly wouldn't
want to rule that view out a
priority I mean it's it's obvious that
we're embedded in in much bigger
systems and I think we understand
essentially nothing about the cognitive
capacities of those
systems
yeah
Michael yeah yeah I I think I think
that's a really important question and I
I think a lot about the perspective of
let's say you know if you were a neural
network or something like this being
trained and so on what would the
perspective of a sub component of that
be where you know let's say if if you
had the capacity as a neuron to sort of
look around and ask yourself you know do
I do I live in a cold Mechanical
Universe that doesn't care what happens
or uh is there some some sort of agency
in my environment that you know am I
when when I'm as as a piece of that
network am I am I learning from my
environment or am I being trained right
because when you're being trained right
there real question is like how many how
many um agents are there in that
interaction is it just you learning as
you will you're the boss and you're sort
of learning whatever from your
environment or are you actually being
trained because the environment is an
agent with an agenda that is training
you for some particular purpose right
and so so this question of uh how would
you know so so you look around and you
you say to yourself well if you're a
piece of this of this network and it's
being trained for some image image
recognition task you know you you would
be I I think wrong to come to the
conclusion that you live in a in a
Mechanical Universe you would you should
come to the conclusion that it's
actually it's it's clearly rewarding you
and punishing you for for specific
things it's not neutral with respect to
what you do and for some reason it
really likes it when you find you know
you find um pictures of dog eyes or
something like this and you have no idea
that what it what it does is recognize
dog faces out of you know all the other
all the other inputs so no doubt there's
some kind of gelian limit to to Fig to
be able to actually understand what the
larger system is doing but I wonder if
we can even have some evidence that just
just for the fact that yes there is a
greater you know sort of a agential
dynamic going on in which I'm caught up
even if you're not able to you know sort
of comprehend what that's going to what
that's going to be I I I don't know I
don't know what that's going to look
like but I think it's pretty important
and I think as as Chris said we really
don't have a very good science at all of
trying to predict or control uh the
cognitive capacities of systems made up
of parts so so we can know many things
about Parts cells robotics whatever and
and we routinely make these larger
systems have then and then get surprised
about what it does or doesn't do or what
what what the goals are going to be what
goals is it capable of pursuing what
preferences does it have this is
probably an existential level um job for
for society is to is to get a good
science of of that of that
going you have done that though haven't
you well we've started
anyway I mean you could no I would go
further than that I I think I think your
work would represent a substantive and
established um formal framework to
address exactly those those issues um
and you can see your embryonic versions
arising in many different fields I just
um came back from a meeting um of
economists and financiers and they are
trying to make the move from behavioral
economics to cognitive economics and
they were exactly addressing these kind
of issues you're understanding the um
the notion of distributed cognition in a
market um so you know and ultimately
they'll become they'll come knocking at
your door I can see that I can see
exactly the SE sequence of people um you
know searching around for people to talk
about um
Illuminating that realization that the I
mean it comes back to what we were
talking about before where You' started
and I was picking up on the um on the
the link between different scales of
self-organization where every scale has
you know complies with the same
principles but how does that
contextualize and I think one really
interesting example of that um is to
think about an individual in an ensemble
or a society and just to wrestle the
argument back to pick up on something
that Chris was saying but you know you
know if if there is a bright line
between the kind of um mechanics that
would qualify as um conscious in the
sense of being um self-aware and I'm
distinguishing that from the kind of
Consciousness that would just entail
qualitative experience you know a loss
of phenomenal transparency so I'm
talking about now self-awareness is you
know one of one of the bright lines that
may be very blur blurry and vague but
certainly one which is induced by the
hard
problem you're just asking a simple
question you what kind of explanation
for my world whether I'm a single neuron
or a single person um would um enable me
or Justify the notion that I am
a um and the obvious answer is um when I
have to disambiguate between the
consequences of my action and your
action if you are very similar to me so
if I you know manag to survive in on an
alien planet where there are no
structures like like me that could cause
the same sensed
consequences uh then there would be no
problem inferring did I cause that or
did you cause that so just having um the
existence of a population of
conspecifics in some sort of formal
structural sense suddenly induces the
inference problem did you cause that or
do I cause that and because that
naturally calls for generative models or
internal Dynamics representations on the
inside
um that entertain the hypothesis on the
notion that that's me as opposed to not
me so you get for free in and only in
this context where you've put lots of
these particles together the you know
the if you like the license or the
motivation to have a hypothesis um you a
representation of selfhood um that you
know from the statisticians point of
view is exactly the justification for
the increased complexity that Chris was
talking about so I I was listening to
that really interesting sort of uh um
sort of Nod to IIT and all it brings to
the table in terms of this sort of you
know commitment to some threshold
Crossing or trans traversing a cut with
increasing complexity but why I mean one
simple answer is that um you if you ask
a statistician what is complexity and
they'll tell you well um it's basically
the degrees of freedom you're using up
to explain some sensory data um you
could articulate it as a k or relative
entropy between a post a prior if you're
a basian but in essence it's just the
degrees of freedom you're um using in
order to accurately explain these data
so mathematically the evidence is equal
to the accuracy minus the complexity so
why would you need what why why is that
useful well an increase in complexity Li
is only licensed by an increase in the
accuracy so the simple argument would go
um if I am obliged to model and predict
and explain a world and that is
constituted by other things like me um
then the accuracy of my predictions will
be greatly enhanced if I have a
representation of me as distinct from
you and if that um entails an increase
in the degrees of freedom namely adding
in this extra kind of H hypthesis and
everything that it entails then um I'm
going to have greater complexity but
it's a complexity that is more than pay
for by the uh by the incre increase in
the accuracy and I you know just coming
back to know my original Point um yeah I
think a lot of the work um that you've
done at the cellular
level um would be very gracefully
translated to the societal level and to
things like economics and to uh Eon
Niche construction um in ethology um and
I know uh Chris is probably wanting to
say this you but language as one way of
facilitating that notion that ability to
um to efficiently with minimum
complexity in this instance um do this
distributed cognition so I'm both train
being trained and learning at the same
time and we're doing it together to
evince some kind of generalized
synchrony so I mentioned language for
for Chris
that the fun hope he wants to pick that
one
up oh well well again what I'd actually
like to do is back up a little bit and
uh put some of what you just said into
very simple active inference
language uh if if I see something
happening on my Markov blanket on my
interface with the
world then I always have the
question uh did I do that or did the
world do
that where the world means everything
outside
me
and in a sense the answer is always the
world did it so the question
becomes did the world do that in
response to something I did to it or did
it just do
it not not in consequence of of any of
my
actions and soone gets immediately to
this kind of babbling scenario that
we've talked about many times uh in
which an infant or a robot or some
system is trying to figure out by
measuring
correlations whether the world's inputs
to it have anything to do with its
inputs to the world
and just asking that question requires
enormous representative
capacity uh because one has to represent
one's
actions and represent them pretty well
in
time and one has
to have a good
memory to represent enough actions to
get any kind of statistical support for
drawing an inference about
correlation
and that memory has to be represented as
a
memory uh not just part of one's
occurrent
input so I think this question that you
posed is really the key question faced
by any agent at all that's trying to get
a model off the ground uh which which in
a sense gets back to to the question
that Mike asked early early on about how
does this all
start uh maybe it starts with
babbling in very simple
systems you know I I was thinking
recently uh this this this whole issue
of of how many agents are there and
where is the border between the agent
and the world and how do you self- model
that border is is a fascinating topic
and there's a there's an amazing um uh
developmental model for this which is
which is that you know we often talk
about one embryo and the embryo does
this and the embryo does that but
actually what happens at the beginning
let's say for example in amniote embryos
is that there's a there's a flat blasted
disc which has just a few cell layers
thick so it's kind of think of it like a
like a Frisbee and it just has a few sub
layers and normally what has to happen
is that one point in this in this disc
breaks Symmetry and then organizes the
primary axis of the first embryo and
basically tells all the other cells
don't do it because because I'm doing it
and that's how you end up with one
embryo now that process is very easily
perturbed and and I many people have
done it I used to do it in my in my
graduate work and what you can do is if
you perturb that process that initial
blasted disc that undifferentiated sort
of pool of of cells which are these sort
of Proto uh low-level Proto Proto agents
that pool can break up into not one
embryo but actually multiple and so you
can have so I did this in in bird
embryos and you can have twins and chick
and and Duck and things like this you
can have and humans humans have exactly
the same structure um you can get them
head-to-head you can have get them side
by side you can get all sorts of
geometries you can get triplets you can
get multiple individuals AR emerging by
different partitions of this of this um
really kind of um medium this
particulate medium where where you have
a bunch of cells and you don't know
ahead of time how many individuals at
the level of how many larger individuals
so embryos are going to arise from this
medium because the the the Dynamics by
which and that's you know local
activation and long range inhibition and
things like that the the Dynamics that
break up that that undifferentiated
ocean of of potential selves into one
two or three or more selves is actually
um it's it's very Dynamic it can it can
go different ways and then you get
interesting interesting things like this
so for example you might know that human
conjoin twins that are you know sort of
stuck together side to side one of the
twins often has leftright asymmetry
defects and it's because when you have
two twins side by side the cells in the
middle both twins can't quite agree on
who they belong to are they the right
side of this twin or are they the left
side of that twin and both twins think
they belong to them but in fact they're
overlapping the same cells and so one
side will have correct left and right
the other guy the other side will have
like two rights for example right and
this ends up this ends up giving one of
the twins laterality defects with
respect to heart and gut patterning and
so so their models each twins as as the
collective of cells tries to compute uh
things like which which where things are
and what's left and what's right and so
on their models can disagree with each
other they can they can draw the
boundary between self and World in
different ways and you can have these
sort of disputes over certain areas as
to where who they actually belong to and
and so so I'm just I'm just incredibly
interested in this in this process of of
emerging of of individualization so to
speak out of this like ocean of of
potentiality these cells you know 50,000
cells and some number of individuals at
the um at the embryo level will be
formed and each of them will have
specific goals in morphospace each of
them will try to achieve very specific
morphologies uh and uh and they've and
then you don't know ahead of time how
many there were going to be you
know Carl what occurs to you when you
hear that um ambiguity um again sort of
um just thinking about the imperatives
for
self-organization so when I hear that
was a fascinating story um and don't let
me forget we explain to the viewers what
babbling means just in this context as
well because that's I quite Illuminating
perhaps we can I'm not sure that the
cells do Mo do motor babbling um but
they certainly resolve um the same kind
of problem um so my um Chris correct me
if I'm wrong but by babbling all we mean
is that when you're first born into any
Universe you've got to um work out or
test the hypothesis that I cause that or
the world caused that um so you don't
know you don't have a self model you
don't you know whether this is sort of
um a declarative model completely
subpersonal just um hardwired into the
um the synaptic efficacy and
connectivity of your brain so the first
thing you have to do is just to work out
what you can control and what you can't
control um and the idea is that you you
um engage in um what I would call
epistemic uh or respond to epistemic
affordances or epistemic plans that
reveal knowledge they resolve
uncertainty and in this instance it's
the uncertainty about whether um I was
the cause of this rattle rattling so if
you imagine um motor babbling um as um
manifest in a little baby um you know
rattling its rattle generating both the
sensations from the muscles and the skin
but also the visual
and the auditory Sensations that all
co-occur providing definitive evidence
that there's something special about
this process and this event that um that
provides the basis for the hypothesis
there's a unitary cause there's a
unitary cause which is me shaking the
rattle but of course it may take several
months if not years to actually get uh
to actually realize that causes me so
one can imagine sort of you know robots
learning about the uh the manipulanda
that they can articulate or the the way
in which they can move around and you
know um
perambulate um but I think the idea
bring it back to sort of where does
selfhood come from
um it would um rest upon the testing the
hypothesis which has to be physically
represented with a deep more complex
generative model and sense making um
that in fact it's me that's actually
caused this single cause of all these
proceptive um motor Sensations visual
Sensations auditory Sensations um and
that will be especially preent when
you're starting to realize that some of
these causes which you thought were you
of the sort associated with nurturing
and suckling um were actually due to Mom
and we come back to this argument to to
actually have a good hypothesis which
explains why I am not in charge of mom
because she is now not always responding
to me when I cry to to explain that I
have to now develop a hypothesis yes it
was me causing all of this um but
sometimes there's something else else
out there that's not me but very much
like me and that's Mom and then you can
see how there would be a pressure in
terms of you know finding the best
explanations for your Sensations to to
have that so if you take that notion now
think of the same problem from the point
of view of a cell
um you know what are the imper or a
bunch of cells that have to work
together or will ultimately form a an
embryo via this process of symmetry
breaking you you know you have to ask
what are the underlying imperatives how
how could it be any other way um and of
course it could be M say it could be
lots of ways but the ways the ways in
which it goes wrong um which would be
another way of saying um those rare
occasions or the the ways that it
doesn't happen in um in consequence of
their Rarity um involve this ambiguity
again literally in this the context of
some cells not knowing whether they're
you're belonging to one twin or or
another twin from the from the cell
perspective um so um I was just thinking
about the nature of ambiguity and of
course you it is exactly the same um one
can
account for the
simple observation that
self-organization does not tolerate
ambiguity it does not tolerate
uncertainty it it's only um manifest in
the context of accurate and um
well-evidenced
definitive uh exchanges so I come back
to Chris's notion of you know sense
making projecting onto my markof blanket
or my holographic screen from the point
of view of the quantum formulation then
I need to resolve all the uncertainty uh
as much uncertainty as I can but put
that another way um in a more slightly
more deflationary way stuff which we see
the way the universe seems to work is um
can be described as um realizing
processes that minimize this this kind
of uncertainty and ambiguity and simply
maximize the mutual predictability of
what's being projected or impressed upon
my surf face on my holographic screen or
my Markoff blanket uh so I you know
that's what I that was going through my
mind I thought was a beautiful example
of of you know uh when it goes wrong
the there uncertainty and ambiguity your
in the game and uh and that tells you
something quite fundamental about when
it goes right and when it goes right is
just basically um a statement of what
exists and you know what what perseveres
you over time Chris did you have
anything to say to add to that well I
would be interested to uh to see how
actually
uh Mike responds
to that uh discourse with respect to the
example of this embryonic sheet where
the cells are each trying to figure out
what they're supposed to
do uh and
there's they're still uh they still
certainly believe that they should be
reproducing so they they definitely do
that and they signal to each other but
somehow they're the collective effect of
all of that signaling to each other is
to organize different roles for the for
each for
themselves so how does the Symmetry
breaking
occur yeah so so that's that's really
interesting so as I as I was hearing um
Carl talk about this I realized a couple
of things that um first of all uh as as
we were saying before feedback loops are
absolutely Central to this process
because the easiest way to prevent any
of this from happening and to end up
with a um kind of a mono um you know
sort of you know very featureless sheet
to where there are no embryos is to
block that is to block the positive
feedback loop that so so that long that
that short range inhibition long range
activation that says to one cell I'm
going to now be the organizer I'm going
to make this access everybody else don't
do it you those are both feedback loops
and so if you break those feedback loops
you get nothing so so the feedback loops
are right at the beginning of this
process and and the other thing that
that I thought was really interesting
that Carl just said is about the cells
babbling so what I think uh it's a
really good name for what we see when
you take a cell and you put it out into
a dish what you'll see you'll and in
fact in any in any new environment you
will see two things that I think are
probably babbling in different spaces
one is that in physical space you will
see that it's incred L active it's
constantly putting out and pulling back
these these um kind of extensions so
these cytoplasmic extensions that have
all kinds of sensors on them they're not
just sitting the cell is never just
sitting there waiting for something to
happen it's constantly probing its
environment it's incredibly active I'm
sure it's taking all kinds of energy it
costs to to do all this um there are
videos of it that are just remarkable on
online and you know we see them every
day the other the other babbling takes
place in transcriptional space so gene
expression is also never just sort of
still and this is you know these are the
Gen that are expressed and I'm just
going to sit here and and do that all
the genes are constantly going up and
down within specific ranges as it sort
of Wiggles in this transcriptional space
and I think both and probably
physiologically metabolically I bet I
bet this is going on in all these other
spaces and I think babbling is an
excellent uh a framework for for
understanding what it's actually doing
it's actually taking these little
actions looking for evidence of specific
things that it can then make use of to
start to draw you know to draw
boundaries and and as Chris as Chris was
saying I think what happens is that in
this blastoderm you get uh what what
what will happen is that once once that
that individuation starts where there's
a specific cell that starts to go down
this road of uh being the organizer of
this new larger Collective it
immediately begins to distort the action
space for all the nearby cells it starts
putting out all kinds of signals reward
you know reward signals and and and
physical forces and all these other
things that now are going to bend the uh
the option for all the other cells and
the best example of that we have are
these zenbot where the these things are
just made of embrionic skin cells and if
you look at a standard old embryo you
get this idea that well what do skin
cells want to do they want to be a
passive two-dimensional layer on the
outside of the animal they do nothing
except sit there keep out the bacteria
you know nice and a boring
two-dimensional life but what you find
out is that that's only true because the
other cells are basically bullying them
into it left to their own devices with
the in the absence of these instructive
interactions with the rest of the embrio
what they what the skin cells actually
want to do is get together into a
three-dimensional uh kind of ball like
architecture they are self motile that
you know they'll run around and move and
do VAR have various behaviors including
make copies of themselves if provided
with materials and so that is completely
um kind of obscured by standard
development where what you're seeing
actually is is cells in a space that was
really deformed by by all their
neighbors right and that's you know that
kind of process that that that starts to
div you know make make those
distinctions where the embo the embryo
can tell what part what parts are inside
and what parts are supposedly outside of
itself and that's that gets reinforced
by all these early
activities Carl or or Chris do you want
to jump in on that I think I think we've
been describing pyus that says basically
that it's curiosity all the way
down every system is trying to figure
out what's going on I was struck with
that with this image of the little cells
putting out fingers you know this is
expiration you know sort of True Blue
expiration and mathematically it's
simply as Chris says it's um what EXC
what what artificial intelligence um
research aspires to which is artificial
curiosity you know going out there
getting the right kind of data um that's
going to maximally resolve your
uncertainty and paint the way the way
forward and of course it's intimately
related to planning and the sense you
have to um realize that palpation you
whether it's a little cell palpating
with its filer or podia or um whether
it's me palpating my visual World by
move my eyes around or whether it's the
um the little baby babbling and
palpating its cot this this this this
palpation has to be planned it could be
planned in the sense of the gazelle CH
sorry the g not the gazelle the cheetah
chasing the gazelle uh so it doesn't
have to be very sophisticated cognitive
conscious planning but certainly has to
has to be planned it has to have this
sort of Cur curious behavior um and You
Know It just strikes me that that is
such a
fundamental um aspect that I think um
would
qualify behaviors that have that aspect
as cognitive in some sense and it's so
fundamental because of course it's it's
just an expression of dynamics that are
apply to um action upon the world um
that
underwrite everything that we do as
certainly as scientists and one could
imagine as as as human beings but
certainly as scientists you know the the
maths of curiosity was was actually
worked out um by Dennis Lindley in the
1950s um in terms of expected
information game and then reintroduced
by people like David McKay in the
context of active learning so bringing
this active notion that you can learn by
actively acquiring the right kind of
data that optimizes that kind of
learning and it became known as
um um the uh principles of optimum Basin
experimental design so it's exactly the
same kind of curiosity that we as
scientists use all the time whenever we
design an experiment it's basically
configuring actively configuring some
process to generate something that can
be sensed or measured that that
maximally resolves our uncertainty or
fors the greatest amount of information
so I mean you know U the three of us as
scientists have become um experts at
this kind of formal curiosity simply you
know just by acquiring knowledge about
in the in the particular paradigms or
setups and Fields that we find ourselves
in the right way to do experiments but
you could argue that that's life you
know in a sense that is the the infant
bubbling uh it is you know it that kind
of sense making getting actively getting
the right kind of data to work out your
place in the world uh to work out what
you know what you should do next is one
of the most existentially important
imperatives and and you know I was
struck at you but the mechanics that
Mike was talking about in terms of the
you know uh the little skin cells left
of their own device is having a party
and forming balls and wandering around I
mean you know one could apply that kind
of mechanics to people can't couldn't
you or even even cultures and countries
we're all trying to find our place and
we're all trying to work out how to
respond to those constraints people
around us at many different scales um um
you put on our behavior and try and
infer well how am I meant to behave in
this situation so even if we all start
off with the same genetic code in the
same sort of model of you know how
people
behave the context in which we find
ourselves now needs to be inferred in
order to have to know how to behave in
this context either as a child or as a
mother as a politician or as an aid
worker or a first responder whatever you
want you have to make that inference and
of course that inference inferring that
context requires the cous behavior that
that that Chris had picked up on in
Mike's
example wow could could could you know
what I'd love to hear is each of you
talk about um what is the simplest most
basic uh thing so you know hopefully
going down to like physics prior to life
but but wherever you like what is the
most basic thing that is able to do that
because that's what I find in in in
talking about this stuff to other
communities the thing that people are
the most resistant to is this idea that
these kind of Dynamics this this kind of
uh EXP ation curiosity prediction all of
these things that we're talking about
that you know people people think it's
it's brains first and then you can do
all these these these great things I I
would love to hear um you know what you
think is the simplest physical system
that can do that kind of thing so that
we can talk about how far down it
actually
goes while Chris is thinking about that
with a profound answer I'll give
you not a trivial answer but a formal um
answer
uh I I think it's um you'd have to
identify the um the depth of planning um
that underwrote the the Dynamics of the
behavior of the system um in question um
and that would be basically if you were
putting this in a sort of path intrical
formulation it would be the sort of the
the amount of time over which you are
integrating your paths and you're
evaluating the best way forward um um
once you move once you move from uh very
short time scales um then the depth of
that planning I think eludes um physical
realizations that could be written down
in terms of um um representations in
terms of concentrations and uh um
depolarizations and the like um and one
has to move to a quantal Street time
representation so you know I guess I'm
basically make making the difference
between the sort of um the the the kind
of Dynamics you'd find in a uh in chemot
taxis or a thermostat um that could be
written down as differential equations
in fact M you're the kind of
differential equations we used in one of
those early um patent formation papers
knowing your place uh approaches um
where everything could be articulated
terms of differential equations so that
there is a kind of planning but it's not
of the Curious kind that we talked about
it's just following the most most likely
Paths of of least action so I would say
that they're not cognitive in the sense
that they they have planning um so I put
chemotaxis and thermostats and possibly
most viruses probably at a precognitive
um or protoc cognitive level but as soon
as you get to um um generative models
that can roll out deep into the future
and I I repeat just when you try to
implement this in silico you know using
computer simulations you really have to
move to a discrete time
representation um which I think is a
non-trivial thing I mean just for
example remember the sort of the eye
movement example yeah we sense make by
getting little snapshots of the world
every 250 milliseconds uh it's not like
I've got I'm a thermostat and I'm taking
a continuous record of the temperature
that is a continuous I'm actually
getting discret quantal observations um
and I think once you move to that kind
of generative model or biophysics that
entails um the gradient flows under that
generative model um then I think you're
in a position to talk about sort of
planning and cognition and curiosity of
the kind that we we're talking about uh
so I you know I'd literally put time
constants on this I'd say about you know
300 milliseconds if you got the ability
to represent the future 300 milliseconds
in in your sorry represent the
consequences of your actions more than
300 milliseconds in the future then I
put you in you know having crossed that
one of those cuts um and move from from
being a sort of um yeah a virus to to
you to to I don't know perhaps an insect
I'm not
sure are you seriously putting the 300
MCS forward or like or is that fa
fous um it's it's fous but but not as
factious as it might as you might think
I do think that there you know I think
there's a there's one way of celebrating
the um the escapes from psychism that we
started off with when you know when Mike
was saying what he spends his time
talking about one of the ways is to
commit to vagueness and you know how
many um how many grains of s do I need
before this ceases or becomes a pile um
and try and work out what the U what the
quantity is uh that defines that
spectrum that we were talking about
before uh along which there is vagueness
at some point consciousness of a certain
kind um um arises um but I also think
there are natural kinds that that
actually have bright lines between them
um and you know what I'm saying here and
I I don't think I've said it before and
I probably wouldn't say it again um U
but um unless I simulated it but there
certainly in my experience qualitatively
different kinds of generative models
that represent time in very very
different ways you can get so
mathematically things like cman filters
that can be cast or linear quadratic
control and
Robotics and the like that can be cast
purely in terms of Futures that are
represented in terms of velocities and
accelerations and higher order motions
that are just in the Dynamics and the
equations of motion uh and you can
realize and build these things you can
simulate them and they behave u in a
very plausible way you can get them to
do handwriting you can get them to
self-organize and do all sorts of
interesting things Al thermostat um but
that's um that's as far as it goes these
things don't show Curious Behavior to do
curious Behavior You' really got to roll
out much further into the future um and
in running out further into the future
it's very difficult to represent the
future just using differential equations
unless you move to very very high orders
of motion at which point you start to
sort of to minimize that complexity
start to articulate things in discrete
time and then the maths sorry the math
the new um the um numerics become much
simpler and doable um and um but then
you've got a qualitatively different
kind of generative mod you move from a
continuous to a discreete time a Quant
quantized generative model um so that
for me is not uh does not allow a
vagueness you know there is actually a
natural kind that will represent things
in the moment in terms of flows and
Dynamics and other natural kinds that
will represent things um in terms of
discrete not universal clock time but
discrete iterations um and I'm saying
that the you know for for certainly our
scale of interactions in the way that we
sense make I would have thought freom of
seconds was not controversial um I say
that because that's the moment it's also
the time interval between the way that
we sample the world not just with our
eyes but when we sniff we sniff at a
frequency which means that each new
sampling of that world that palpation
with our chemo receptors and Factory
receptors is again every you know every
200 milliseconds so so just to me
there's a sort of discreet belief
updating um and if there a discret
belief updating that is underwritten by
the way we act that the plans have to be
these discrete chunks of time so that's
where the 300 milliseconds come from you
see it everywhere mice whisking they
whisk at that frequency so they touch
and palpate every 300 milliseconds the
way I'm speaking now every phoning is
reaching your ears every 300
milliseconds or so
or or possibly less so wherever you look
in our biological scale that's there
does seem to be this sort of
characteristic uh time stamp that's
purely empirical
so the phous aspect inherits from the
fact that that's that's very egocentric
it's just for things like me I don't
know if it's for things like cells or
quantum physics well it's interesting
because in physics the number three has
an interesting role in fundamental
physics because there's three
generations of of matter and there's the
number three CRS up and it's a mystery
as to why so it sounds like the number
300 or 300 millisecond a unit attached
to it or Neuroscience maybe a a
fundamental constant so Chris what are
some of the deep thoughts that you were
having well I I was just having a visual
impression actually when Mike was
talking and
um of of
babbling and the visual impression was
of our our sort of model of the quantum
vacuum and
we think of when we think of the
vacuum or at least I think of it uh
visually as as little things popping in
and out of existence all the
time and
so one could think of that as a as a
kind of babbling right the the field
itself is exploring what's going on
outside of
itself that's extremely interesting by
uh forming a little entity to go off and
and explore and then report
back so this is a this is a very
different picture from the one that that
Carl gave in that um but I suppose it
also has a similarity or
two that when we write
down a a model of that activity it is
discreet it is operating in in a
discrete kind by generating discrete
events
even though it's it's modeled in a
continuous SpaceTime
which
uh once one digs a little bit deeply The
Continuous FaceTime itself becomes
discreet
but this raises a question for me which
is another of the things that I think
about a
lot
um which is the question
of what what we mean by
Randomness
and suddenly to take a basian point of
view where probabilities are all
subjective uh it becomes very difficult
to say what Randomness might mean if if
used in a way that's meant to be
objective or to refer to something
objective and we model things like
fluctuations in the vacuum as
random uh which from a a basian point of
view just
means it's uncertain to us it represents
information that we don't have and quite
possibly can't get even in
principle but if we think of that system
as an
agent then of course you're expected to
be exploring its World whatever it is
whatever uh exists that's not
it
and maybe uh we can really think of
babbling all the way down as a model of
of what's happening in these phenomena
that we persist in thinking of as
random uh but we also don't typically
think of these sorts of systems as
agents this this is this is incredibly
interesting um what I heard what I heard
Carl saying among other things is that
there there is a there is a qualitative
transition when things go from analog to
digital in a certain sense right from
from from continuous to to to phase and
based on what Chris just said of it just
remind us to to think about the kind of
the quantum world where at least to my
understanding a lot of things are in
fact you know sort of discreet does that
mean that really could it be that that
that is the sort of Base State as Chris
just outlined with with with that kind
of protoc cognitive exploration all all
the way down and that these continuous
models that we put on top of it by by by
corar graining um you know tiny events
into the kind of macroscopic things that
we see here that's that's an abstraction
that sort of loses the essential uh
mindfulness of it and then we have to
try to rebuild it again by the time we
get to brains but actually all we've
done is obscure the the fact that all
the way from the beginning it was
already digital to start with and we
just sort of put some put some Vaseline
in our lens here you know to make
everything look um you know sort of
continuous which then which then made it
look like there was nothing going on at
the lower levels and then then somehow
we're we're shocked that we have to
recover it from from somewhere later on
that that's that's what I just heard
from the combination of those two um
explanations it's a very interesting
idea and it connects nicely to the
history of
mathematics or at least the history of
mathematics
post decard and liet which was all built
around the idea of continuous functions
and Analysis and calculus and so
on very very nice convenient mathematics
to
use but
uh obscure it in a certain
way Carl did you have any thoughts to
add to
that um yeah I probably um this is why I
wanted to hang out with with Mike and
Chris to learn about Quantum Theory
because I do think there's something
fundamental about this sort of you the
way that we carve up the world or the
world the way the world can only be
defined in a carved way into tiles or
Quanto or discret things um so um I I
think
that those observations that we just
heard I think are quite fundamental um
and it would be great to understand um
everything from a sort of quantal
perspective or disti perspective and how
continuous constructs like you know
space and time emerge from that um you
if necessary um having said that um I
have to say that um as a physicist I
would bring something else to the table
so I'm I'm quite comfortable dealing
with random fluctuations so for me
random fluctuations are are just
variables that change very very quickly
so if I want to write down um as a
physicist so now I and I'm talking about
a physicist that doesn't know anything
about quantum mechanics um so I just
want to write down a long van equation
to describe my universe um I write it as
a mixture of states and random
fluctuations and somebody asked me what
license is that I just well the r
fluctuations are very very quick and the
uh the states are very very slow um and
this is just a natural consequence of um
some kind of renormalization group you
know I I I could uh make them even
slower by going to the next St scale and
throw some even more fast stuff so
there's nothing really if you like um
problematic from the point of view of
that kind of physicist um in in the
random
fluctuations um uh it just means that
all the stuff that determines flows and
dynamics of the kind that we can um that
we engage with and we can plan um has a
particular form and that particular form
um
does actually bring a quantal aspect um
to the table or a discretization aspect
of the table that may or may not be if
you like um explained away or absorbed
into a Quantum information theoretic
treatment but what I'm talking about
here um are the mathematical image of
light life cycles and biorhythms and
oscillations and I mean that right from
you know the perspective of a dendr in
my hippocampus oscillating away a fast
gamma frequency you know sort of say 80
htz through to the the motion of the
heavenly bodies wherever you look you
get the this um solenoidal
flow um that is characteristic of things
that hang around and don't dissipate
almost immediately um uh and these are
not part of the random FL in fact they
become more evident as you go away from
the fast random stuff into the slow um
the slow uh Dynamics um in the sense
that you know clearly uh the orbit of
the moon around well the orbit of the
Earth around the Sun for example this
deals with very very massive large
things where all the random fluctuations
are effectively averaged to zero um
whereas if you go down to the quantum
scale um then you know you're not
licensed to do that and these solenoidal
flows um become much less um much less
apparent but our our scale if we are if
life is um on this reading of physics um
um sufficiently classical to have um
oscillations bi rhythms um things that
would you need full feedback that didn't
go off to plus and minus infinity for
example just saying that you're keeping
you're circulating in some state or
phase space in a way that you keep
yourself to some attracting set and as
you move through this you are naturally
going to be oscillating your in a highly
nonlinear possibly chaotic way but still
the essence is life cycles if that's the
case then the ponari section does indeed
permit a description that is necessarily
discretized in the sense you're going to
pass through the neighborhood of various
States at discrete points in time um um
uh recurrently um so that's what I was
thinking from the point of view of a
physicist who who does not have the
fluency of quantum mechanics to get back
to a discreet thing but it also I think
um highlights the um the Deep connection
between things recurring discreetly or
occurring uh discreetly um um um being
one way of defining another
characteristic of of biological self
organization which is basically bi
rhythms and and life cycles uh that have
this sort of self-contained I Y and of
course in that self-containment you've
got this natural resolution of ambiguity
and uncertainty because you always know
you're you're on the same itinerant path
repeatedly visiting the states that you
once occupied so that that that's what I
would say from the point of view of
physicist I may say something very
different in a few years time when I've
learned more about Quantum Theory so let
me ask Chris could you ever describe
that kind of mathemat physicists
treatment of Dynamics in pure Quantum
information Theory at that at that kind
of
scale well I I think if we if we try to
think of scaling up from
from
um descriptions of things like Quantum
Fields then this looks
impossible but uh if we think of
it informationally maybe it doesn't look
impossible I'll I'll go back to John
Wheeler's notion that a bit is
fundamentally the answer to a yes or no
question and information the information
theory is about bits and systems that
exchange
bits
but
what do you mind repeating that last
part but what what Wheeler's aphorism
doesn't specify is the complexity of the
question that has a yes or no
answer so in in your case Carl you have
an oscillatory system that passes after
a discrete time of particular
boundary so the the system May well be
asking the question have I passed this
boundary and the answer is yes or no or
am I passing the boundary right now well
that's one
it uh that's a yes or no question but
it's an extremely complicated
question so it may be that we can
develop uh a theory that leaves the
complexity of the generative model
unspecified and
concentrates just on the bitf
flow across the
boundary that counts as evidence in One
Direction and perturbative action in the
other
direction and and then I think the two
pictures fit together rather nicely
because one can imagine the generative
model operating it that the generary
model being the model that generates the
questions um operating at many different
scales where where one could think of
the scales as computational complexity
and this gets back in a sense to your
question about
language uh language is a way of posing
questions it's a way of babbling in the
world and this process of babbling it
seems to me as far as I understand it's
like poking and prodding to test your
own self model to see what's the
difference between me and the world it
sounds like that never stops even though
we call it babbling as if do it does it
ever stop are we not engaging in this
right now and I like this phrase
babbling all the way down I'm going to
put that on a t-shirt by the way Chris
or and it also by the way seems like
babbling all the way up too because
we're constantly engaging in this so
firstly is that true does babbling have
an end and and also does it not presume
a self in order to test the self what I
mean is Carl when you were speaking
about the process of babbling it's the
infant doing something on the world in
order to make a model but that that
first part was it's it is doing
something to the world to me already
presumes the external World whereas the
way that I'm understanding it is that
the self is a model but it's also in
your point of view it's something
objective and I believe from my readings
of Chris I don't I believe Chris is more
on the non-u end where it's it's it's
that's less the case so I'm unsure
anyway I just said a slooh so please
respond to it as you as you wish right
well I mean just to um dispel the notion
that the self is um objective now I I
didn't mean that I I meant it exactly
the same way that um I think both Chris
and Mike could been intimating that you
know from the inside of a cell or a
person or the baby's skull um you self
um is you know quite a sophisticated um
construct um you know fantasy hypothesis
um that is physically realized possibly
neuronally in some lucky creatures and
some lucky children uh you may actually
find some children never get that far
you I'm thinking here people with severe
autism for example who don't have a a
theory of Mind simply because they never
developed the notion that um um I am a
person um and you know what comes along
with that is that you know if you got
very very severe autism or if you like
so theoretically idealized autism um
that means that personhood doesn't exist
so you would be I would regard you as an
animate fridge or you know some um
interesting autonomous vehicle but you
would never be a person because I don't
I don't have the hypothesis that you
know there are people out there and that
people share certain sort of phenotypic
characteristics and um have intentions
in the same sense that I have intentions
so I just I'm not aware that because I
just don't don't have that hypothesis so
it's a longwinded way of saying that I
didn't mean to imply any objectivity
here I was more going the other way
really I'm just saying that selfhood um
um that would be one part of
Consciousness and if you want to
associate cognition and Consciousness
then per possibly um that kind of
minimal selfhood would you know would be
necessarily part of um of cognition this
is a gift that you have to get by
Crossing one of those bright lines um
and it's just a fantasy that you bring
to the table to make sense of uh all the
Impressions on on your sort of sensory
surface or your holographic screen or
your or your cell surface or so The
receptors you are equipped with um to
sense what's going on out there does
that make sense yeah I know that Mike
and and Chris you may have a response to
that but I just want to quickly respond
to what
Professor fron was saying is so and this
is to both of you how do you then
prevent an existential crisis as you
start to study this so for example Carl
before you and I were speaking and I
told you about some experiences I had
where I've deeply felt what you're
saying is being true that the self is a
fantasy and this Oneness with all this
world being generated in one's mind and
I I felt like that was a to a psychotic
episode and it was extremely
destabilizing and to be quite Frank I'm
I'm still recovering from that
and so I'm unsure how any of you all do
this work without
constantly being in a debilitating state
of of existence well existence is the
question here it's an existential crisis
which I'm inquiring about so how is it
that you prevent yourself from getting
into that how could you say these words
of well the self is is not objective the
self may be a a fantasy quote unquote
but not then be able to to not speak and
and look around you in awe and and
horror at the same time okay so that's a
psychological philosophical question
anyone who wants to take that up I I
think there is a good deal of
existential um what uncertainty involved
in uh in doing what we're doing so just
part for the
chorus
right how do you get over
it I'm not sure when gets over
I I I think it's
more
[Music]
um being comfortable with
it you know I I I I I think you raised a
really a really important point and it's
I think this is in a class of uh a
number of really destabilizing um uh
ideas that one picks up as as one gets
older and studies things and and there
are many of these I remember as a as a
child being completely freaked out by
the fact that I realized that you know
we grow up and we become these adults
these adults bear some resemblance to
the children but they're definitely not
the same thing and so in some sense you
could sort of see it coming it's almost
even even before you realize that you're
going to you know you're going to you're
going to die biologically someday before
long before that you realize that you're
going to undergo some transition that's
going to you know turn you into a
completely different sort of creature
which really you know has some
continuity but maybe not you know
certainly not you persisting in the same
way as you are now right so some kind of
weird butter you know caterpillar
butterfly effect where you're just not
going to be around in that same way as
as you are now right so that's kind of
the first thing you you realize as a
child and then and then there's many
others that sort of you know you learn
about boltzman brains and all the
different you know humean arguments of
but you know all this stuff that you
know I had to I I did um I did a
philosophy class with my son when he was
little uh uh we were doing um
homeschooling and so I kind of did this
and I realized very quickly that I have
to be very careful with this stuff
because if you right somebody who has
the capacity to understand it it's
extremely destabilizing and I think that
uh at this point for myself you know I
sort of go with with deart a little bit
in the following sense I I I'm I'm not
depressed by it in the sense that
whatever we discover is is a truer model
of the self than we may have had it
doesn't it I I don't I don't think
there's any way in which it makes it
less um it makes us less less less
valuable less interesting less
engaging all of that is still true it's
just that now we've realized that a
different set of mechanisms can now
Implement that magic than we thought
right so you may have had sort you know
some sort of um idea that well there has
to be some sort of um different kind of
unique process that makes us permanent
self and therefore I'm this individual
and I have I have uh you know I have
true true beliefs and references and and
I exist in some way I I don't think you
can ever convince yourself that you that
that that isn't true and that you don't
exist it's just that now you find out
that actually the way you get to be that
is by these sets of mechanisms and
they're very interesting it's the sort
of thing that Carl and Chris have been
talking about so that's what gets you to
be this individual this kind of
individual and it's kind of amazing that
that works but that doesn't to me that
doesn't um diminish all of the thing all
of the things that I thought were true
about what the individual actually is
right your reality the real of it that
the imper impermanence is there but we
knew that from the time you were a kid
you knew that it wasn't going to be
permanent so that that part you know you
sort of have to deal with from the start
after that it's all you're learning
after that is just that you were really
mistaken about what it takes to be that
sort of creature you thought maybe it
had to be some magical whatever now you
think that wow it's a set of you know
feedback loops and whatever else so
that's surprising but that's okay we we
learn about you know we learn about
different underpinnings to things all
the time so that's okay but I don't I
don't think any of it diminishes the the
the sort of um just the incredible awe
of of being a sensient a being that can
think about these things yeah just
reiterate that so I I didn't in any way
mean to demean um our selfhood or your
selfhood in particular um by calling it
a fantasy I actually meant it um and
indeed have written about it um in terms
of something quite fantastic so we've
written papers called The Fantastic
organ the brain is a fantastic organ
just because it can produce these
fantasies it's absolutely fantastic and
of course they you know in relation to
our early conversation the capacity to
have these fantasies which have
incredible explanatory power if you can
obtain them and you can maintain them um
is the part of the complexity which
allows us to cross these bright lines or
these gaps and become or cuts and become
um closer to to you know to the kind of
creatures that can can can even
entertain the notion of the hard problem
just
to Mike I just love that meta answer we
don't know what the answer would look I
got to tell Andy Clark about that he'll
tell David Charmers um but to come back
to the point so I didn't mean to demean
that um and you know phrases that I
remember coming across and having to
learn uh when I was a students of things
like existential angst and ontological
security all of these things um you know
rear their face if you are worried about
these things but the very fact that you
are able to entertain the notion that
you are not real is quite remarkable um
and I repeat is a is a gift of a
fantastic sort it is a kind of fantasy
that very few um creatures have and
sometimes even few people have so there
are people who actually will go out
there to try and um experience that and
to become and treasure the uh the gift
of being able to make sense of the world
as me um by taking drugs or doing
mindfulness um therapy uh in order to
actually get to a state where um s of
almost a fraudi Oceanic state where
Sellwood is dissolved so they can
experience it and certainly if you've um
taken um sort of psychedelic drugs in
sufficient quantity um you may have that
kind of experience that's s of
derealization or dissociative experience
which is the realization that you know
your construct your fantasy of selfhood
that is engaged and engaging
continuously and for as long as you live
um then um you know if you want to
appreciate that then you have to
experience you know the alternative
hypothesis uh so you know experiencing
derealization or in this instance
depersonalization um is actually I think
uh one really important step to self
understanding so I don't see it as at
all threatening nor diminishing it's
it's just part of self- understanding
which not everybody gets the opportunity
to indul I me I mean in some you know in
some sense the most destabilizing thing
of all ought to be just the bare facts
of Developmental biology when you learn
that you are in fact not some sort of uh
un indivisible monatic whatever which I
don't even I'm not even sure what that
would entail if you were but but the
fact that we are all like all
intelligences are collective intellig is
We Are All Made of parts and the idea
that you used to be this quiescent oite
this little bag of of chemical reactions
that did very little and then very
slowly sort of Step by Step you turned
into whatever you are now if that's not
destabilizing I don't know what is
because just knowing nothing knowing
nothing else about Evolution or I mean
to me developmental biology is sort of
like the the you know the queen of of of
all the Sciences because just that fact
that you go from from from chemistry and
physics to mind in in nine months plus
however many years it takes uh and that
and that you are literally a collection
of cells that you could see in pond
water more or less is just if if you
know you're you're you're a bunch of
cells in the trench coat you know like
the in the cartoons like if if that's
not destabilizing I don't know what I
don't know what else
is so quickly just I know we have to get
going and I'd like to wrap with a a set
of brief questions but quickly Carl and
perhaps well anyone who would like to
answer what is it that separates those
who are de personal ized or go through
certain psychotic episodes from what is
it that separates those who are
fortunately like myself where it's
abating and I'm able to function and I'm
able to have friends and so on versus
those who go into a ward because
obviously those issues can like you
mentioned it's a gift for some it's not
a gift I felt like for myself would I
don't want that gift I'll return that
gift I wish there was a receipt with it
but and I still actually feel like that
but for some obvious it's it's it's a
horrible and persistent feeling so what
is it that separates
them well I'll answer from the point of
view
of a psychiatrist with a with with a
commitment to sort of a mechanistic or
theoretical understanding I I think it's
um the inability to resolve the um the
uncertainty that is attends entertaining
the Dual hypothesis that I may exist or
I may not exist as me um but as soon as
you increase your hypothesis base you
naturally induce an uncertainty an
ambivalence and um a kind of ambiguity
um so it is exactly the same if you like
um the we're talking about the same
imperatives that we've been talking
about all along which is to sort of
resolve uncertainty resolve ambiguity to
make the most sense of things so if
you've entertained this hypothesis that
you're you are not you and you are you
and you can't fully resolve that then
you will find yourself in a state of
chronic uncertainty that unfortunately
does have pathological consequences um
I'm not sure that being in a pych is
necessarily too pathological I mean you
know there are ways to live very nicely
and constructively and fantastically in
psychs and I've done that I spent two
years in a Therapeutic Community um but
there will be other squel ey of an
inability to resolve uncertainty they're
expressed clinically and physiologically
in terms of anastatic load and the like
and chronic stress and the like which
can be very unpleasant uh and ultimately
can have physical consequences from the
point of view of you know the effects on
your body so the question now is why
can't some people resolve that
uncertainty I think it's then a question
of the the the
biophysical um um processes that enable
you to update your beliefs and build
good models of of Your World um that
again this is a very PR itic answer from
the point of view of you know of of
clinical um of a clinician um uh
probably the answers lie in the way that
your brain has assembled itself to
coordinate and attend to various sources
of evidence um and the it looks at the
mechanisms are underwrite that ability
to deploy attention rest very much upon
neuromodulator neurotransmitters are the
kind you you you'll have heard about in
the popular media and will have read
about things like dopamine ser Onin um
and indeed um um oxytocin all the drugs
that are either used or the targets of
um psychotics or psychedelics or
psychotics or drugs that are used to try
and control some of these feelings and
some of these signs and symptoms you
know uh specifically that attend um
anxiety disorders and um and depression
so you know understanding the uh this is
the not the feedback loops that do
self-organization in the developing
embryo but the the same kinds of
mechanisms that do the feedback loops
and the self organization of different
um structures within the brain um that
can be construed as blankets within
blankets or holographic screens within
holographic screens or cells within
cells um all um complying with the same
principles but in the particular
instance of the brain doing this and
understanding the neurochemistry and the
biophysics
of this fundamental sense making
self-organization um it turns out that
these are certain these neurochemical
messages um are uh particularly
important in resolving that kind of
uncertainty and it may be that you have
either taken drugs or you have just
grown up to not be able to deploy these
neurotransmitters Pro properly um again
leading us to well how would you gain
control of it well you might want to do
mindfulness training meditation and the
like just internal attention State
training basically to mentalize how you
deploy your
attention Mike I know that you had a set
of questions that you're eager to ask
both Carl and Chris did you already get
to all of them uh well that would be
impossible but I got to uh I got to many
I got to many of them uh most of the
important ones I learned I learned a
massive amount today this has been just
amazing um but I will be um pestering
both of them with additional question
questions in you know years to
come great to end I I have a question
that I didn't email you that just
occurred to me as you all were speaking
it's something that Professor Levan that
you said what are some aspects of your
field maybe their theories or concepts
that your peers are extremely resistant
to but you are
not wow um we I don't I don't know if we
got time for all that that that's a lot
that's aot that's a lot of stuff um I
mean the most basic there are many I
mean the most basic thing is this notion
of uh profound symmetries between these
fields uh you know this this idea that
you can um that you can you can
basically import uh um Concepts and
strategies from cognitive Neuroscience
or Behavioral Science and deploy them in
other spaces developmental biology
metabolism that you can that it even
makes sense to talk about um you know
goals memories planning navigation um
all of these kinds of things outside of
what we're used to which is some you
know rat in a maze or or something like
this so so that Continuum this idea that
it goes that that that something
important goes all the way down or or
maybe a long way down even if not all
the way down that that that is uh in in
in a few circles that's okay in most
circles that that I deal with that's
just a that's just you know a complete
heresy um yeah there there are many
others but that's that's kind of a basic
one
Chris well I I I think that Mike really
nailed it with that
answer and
um I would say yes it's it's not a a
popular idea that physics and biology
and psychology are actually all more or
less the same
science but uh I think that they
are professor
friston yeah well that that would be my
favorite heresy I'm just going to agree
with with Mike and Chris you know
physics biology psychology they're all
the same thing and I just wanted to end
by saying uh you know heresy I'm not so
sure anymore I I you know the number of
times for example I see Mike Levan cited
in high-end philosophy journals and
treatments um suggests to me that in
fact it's going to be the minority um in
at least in a few years time that that
don't subscribe to this more holistic um
um um encompassing um and I think um
correct way of of viewing um you know
certainly the life sciences but you know
more generally the Natural Sciences um
uh
so you know who is going to be the
heretic in a few years time I suspect it
won't be any of
us and I'll end with one that I see from
particular Chris and Michael is it
sounds like without using the word it
sounds like what you all are doing
trying to understand God or trying to
come up with a model of God and the
reason why I say that is because with
looking at a neuron and saying okay how
can a neuron look around and have some
model and know that it's embedded in
something higher that sounds to me like
well if we apply that to ourselves and
continually do so we would reach
something akin to God and then Chris
with the quantum babbling if one can
think of it like that well what is
babbling
I know that maybe you all don't want to
use the word God but for me what I I
have that many of my peers are extremely
against would be to philosophize about
God or to explicate God or to take god
seriously as not an old man in the sky
with a beard and so I I see you all as
doing something similar and
I'm I'm happy to be in your company I'm
extremely lucky all science um starts
with an Act of Faith with a very
important Act of Faith which is that the
world is in some way understandable that
we are not just a bubble in this um you
know random universe that just happens
to you know as as a as a as a total
random string of of of coincidence looks
like it's got laws and then and then
tomorrow somewhere you know at while you
sleep the whole thing falls apart and we
go back to a random you know sort of
random distribution of events so we all
there's no proof of any of it of any of
that right we take we have to take that
on faith and that may be for a scientist
that may be the most destabilizing thing
if can't get yourself to believe that
that that the world isn't for some weird
reason understandable and and amendable
at least to some extent to our logic and
probing then then you can't do science
you can't do any of the things that that
we do so so being uh useful and and and
hopefully productive in in what we do
starts with that act of faith that is
just completely to my knowledge it's
it's it's it's it's an AUM it's not
based on any evidence that you could
possibly have so so I do think that sort
of underlies everything that we do just
this idea that we can in fact squeeze
some understanding out of what's going
on around
this I'd also think you'd be surprised I
know that you said that it doesn't
comport with the traditional definition
of God but it depends on what tradition
and how far back one goes because there
are Mystics of let's say Christian
Mystics and is Muslim Mystics or Islamic
Mystics and so on yeah and then
obviously then the Eastern end is much
more
mystical so okay well thank you all so
much for for thank you so much for
coming out to this and thankk you i'
I've learned a tremendous amount and I
hope you all have too I I I'm I'm
blessed and thank you so
much well thank you very much this was
this was a very interesting conversation
and thank you very much for putting it
together yeah absolutely this is this is
great great great idea thanks for having
this song yeah I'm just super pleased
super pleased to have been part of it
yeah it went in directions that I didn't
expect I didn't I don't even think I
looked at my notes my my notepad here I
I wrote some notes but they occurred to
me in the moment okay thank you all Mike
I know you got to get going and and so
it well thank you all all right thank
you cheers cheers thanks bye everyone
bye bye take
care the podcast is now finished if
you'd like to support conversations like
this then do consider going to
patreon.com CT J AI m u n g l that is
Kurt jongle it's support from the
patrons and from the sponsors that allow
me to do this fulltime every dollar
helps trend mously thank you